Alright בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today is דף י. Daf Yud. We
are behind, so we're going to really try to go quickly as
I said
yesterday. Very last line of טז עמוד א, Tes-Zayin Amud Aleph, in
the middle of a major סוגיא Sugya of צדקה, Tzedakah, and here
we go.
אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, בזמן שבית המקדש קיים אדם שוקל
שקלו ומתכפר לו, Zman SheBeis HaMikdash Kayam Adam Shokeil Shiklo U'Mischaper Lo,
he
would
continue, ועכשיו שאין בית המקדש קיים אם עושים צדקה מוטב, v'achshav she'ein
Beis HaMikdash Kayam im osim tzedakah mutav, if you do צדקה tzedakah
it's good. It's interesting to note the, you know we normally think
about תפילה tefillah נגד קרבנות, neged korbanot, and the גמרא Gemara has
now explicitly said צדקה tzedakah נגד קרבנות. neged korbanot. But there've definitely
been some comparisons before learning about the concept of צדקה tzedakah from
you know money that was given to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
and so on. And here more directly that the money you give
serves as a type of a קרבן. korban. אם עושים צדקה מוטב,
Im osim tzedakah mutav, it's good. Okay.
ואם לאו באין עובדי כוכבים ומזיי, V'im lav boi nochbei chachamim u'mezuyei,
you know what? You're going to lose the money anyway. Because there's
another theme that's been introduced we'll come back, which is if you
don't handle taking care of your own poor, then the non-Jewish government
is going to step in and do the job for you and
going to collect taxes and so on, and you would rather take
care of that yourself. ואף על פי כן, V'af al pi kein,
and even though when they step in, נחשב להם לצדקה, nechshav lahem
l'tzedakah, and they force you to give taxes, and the taxes goes
ahead and helps support the poor, it still counts as צדקה, tzedakah,
שנאמר ונוגשיך צדקה, shene'emar v'nogsaich tzedakah,
those that oppress you צדקה, tzedakah, which is the thing they'll oppress
you to get the money and it'll still be צדקה. tzedakah. So
you go ahead and figure out, look look how much money I
already give for צדקה, tzedakah, how much do I give for taxes,
what percentage of the budget of the national and you know budget
goes towards the you know towards the various support system? What do
they call it, you know social security and whatever? Now nothing. What?
Now nothing. Alright. Enough political commentary. Moving on. אמר רבא היינו דאמר
לי עולא, Amar Rava, hainu d'amar li Ulla, the following thing עולא
Ulla said to me.
משגש ארחתיה דאמיה. meshageish archasei d'imei. Now עולא, Ulla, I missed, read
that, the word is not עולא, Ulla, the word is like עויל,
Olel, the the infant child or or the suckling child who perverted
the path of his mother. So that's a very bizarre name, we're
going to see that this name who this name was being given
to, okay, and what this is about. Okay, this was a name
being given to רב ששת, Rav Sheshet, and why and because of
a story we're about to tell. So the following thing רב ששת
Rav Sheshet said to me. משמיה דרבי אלעזר, Mishmei d'Rabbi Elazar, in
the name of רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, top of י עמוד א.
Yud Amud Aleph. מאי דכתיב, Mai d'chsiv, what is meant by the
verse? וילבש צדקה כשרין, v'yilbash tzedakah k'shiryon, and he cloaked himself in
righteousness, of course you have to I mean I'll say it but
I won't keep on saying it, but I think you realize that
so many of the verses if not all of them that talk
about צדקה tzedakah are talking about righteousness, they are not talking about
charity. Okay, the גמרא Gemara is reading this with its the rabbinic
meaning of the word צדקה tzedakah as charity. Okay so the verse
is, you know, he cloaked himself in righteousness like a like a
plate armor, okay, but the גמרא Gemara is reading it as with
צדקה tzedakah like plate armor. So לומר לך, lomar lach, to tell
you מה שריון, ma shiryon, I think that's what it was called,
right, the plate armor, the stuff that goes like like the shingles
type of thing? Okay, so that's what a שריון shiryon is, an
armor that's sort of like these metal shingles essentially. לומר לך, Lomar
lach, to tell
you מה שריון זה כל קליפה וקליפה מצטרפת לשריון גדול, ma shiryon
zeh kol klipa u'klipa mitztarefet l'shiryon gadol, the same way every individual
little like you
know piece of armor piece of like the you know the metal
plate connects to be a major protection, okay, a major plate armor,
אף צדקה כל פרוטה ופרוטה מצטרפת לחשבון גדול, af tzedakah kol pruta
u'pruta mitztarefet l'cheshbon gadol, same way by צדקה, tzedakah, you give a
dollar today, a dollar tomorrow, in the end it adds up to
a million money. Okay. רבי חנינא אמר מהכא, Rabbi Chanina amar meihacha,
רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina says from here. וכבגד עדים כל צדקותינו, U'k'veged
idim kol tzidkoseinu,
like a soiled garment is all of our righteousness. Okay, we don't
have to soiled is what רש"י Rashi says the word is, okay,
or removed garment, but רש"י Rashi says removed, others say soiled. Anyway,
the point is we don't have to worry about that word because
the emphasis is בגד beged here. מה בגד זה כל נימא ונימא
מצטרפת לבגד גדול, Ma beged zeh kol nima u'nima mitztarefet l'veged gadol,
the same way a garment every individual strand you know is nothing
by itself, one little strand of thread, but at the end you
have a real garment, אף צדקה כל פרוטה ופרוטה מצטרפת לחשבון גדול,
af tzedakah kol pruta u'pruta mitztarefet l'cheshbon gadol, in the end it
combines to a big thing, which is interesting by the way also
because you know here it's sort of doing it from the perspective
of the giver, right, it's not like you give a little bit
to an עני ani every day it makes a difference, like here
it's like the reward that you get by giving every little penny
every little dollar you give in the end it becomes a very
big thing, a big amount. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says אמאי
קרי ליה עולא משגש ארחתיה דאמיה, Amai karu lei Ulla meshageish archasei
d'imei, so why did they call, we're finding out this is about
רב ששת, Rav Sheshet, you know this is a strange name, the
suckling who perverted the path of his mother. דבעי מיניה רב אחא
בר אדא מרב ששת, D'bai minei Rav Acha bar Adda meiRav Sheshet,
so here we're going to have a total digression. דבעי מיניה רב
אחא בר אדא מרב ששת, D'bai minei Rav Acha bar Adda meiRav
Sheshet, מנין לצפורי ימי צפורו שמטמאין אדם, minayin l'tzipporei yemei tzipporo she'metam'in
adam, how do you know that a מצורע metzora or or somebody
with צרעת tzara'as that when he is in the process of צפורו
tzipporo which is after he has done the initial... initial purification process,
you did the whole thing with the birds and you sprinkled it
and he has to wait seven days before re-entering the camp. So
what is his level of טומאה tumah during that period? If he
is טמא tamei in order to make another person טמא tamei because
you can only make a person can only become טמא tamei from
אב הטומאה. av hatumah. So does he at this stage become an
אב הטומאה? av hatumah? Is it a ראשון לטומאה? rishon l'tumah? What
is he? So how do you know that he's מטמא אדם? metamei
adam? Gemara says,
so how do you know?
אמר ליה, Amar leh, he is מטמא בגדים, metamei bgadim, he makes
the בגדים bgadim that he's wearing טמא, tamei, so therefore he makes
a person טמא. tamei. אמר ליה, Amar leh,
דילמא, dilma, maybe it's different when it's on him that's
טמא, tamei, but to touch someone, to touch a person or to
touch clothes, maybe it wouldn't make him טמא. tamei. והסט נבילה, V'heses
neveilah,
if somebody moves a נבילה, neveilah, okay, carries or moves a נבילה,
neveilah, it's מטמא בגדים, metamei bgadim, it's מטמא metamei him and the
בגדים bgadim he's wearing. ואינו מטמא אדם, V'eino metamei adam, but now
he does not have the טומאה tumah that somebody he touches will
become טמא. tamei. So it's different if you say that something somebody
is wearing becomes טמא tamei with the person, okay, but that doesn't
mean that the person now has the ability to be מטמא metamei
other things. What's
הסט נבילה? heses neveilah? הסט, Heset, to lift up a נבילה neveilah
like a carcass, a dead carcass of an animal, then you become
טמא tamei and the בגדים bgadim on you are being compared to
a נבילה? neveilah? Picking up a נבילה? neveilah? No. A person who
picks up a נבילה neveilah becomes טמא tamei together with the בגדים
bgadim on him. And even so, that person does not have the
ability to be מטמא metamei other people, okay, because when you with
the בגדים bgadim on you become טמא, tamei, it doesn't prove that
you have the power to be מטמא metamei other things. I see.
So, okay, so the Gemara says, so אמר ליה, amar leh, so
he said back to him, אלא שרץ
דמטמא אדם מנלן? ella sheretz d'metamei adam menalan? How
do you know? Let's take a dead rodent. How do you know
that causes a person to become טמא? tamei? לאו משום דמטמא בגדים?
Lav mishum d'metamei bgadim? Is it not because it can make בגדים
bgadim טמא tamei and therefore it can? So, you know, so therefore
again, he's trying to talk about this comparison between בגדים bgadim making
בגדים bgadim טמא tamei and making a person טמא, tamei, although it
ignores the answer a minute ago about בגדים bgadim that you're wearing
have a different status, because when a dead שרץ sheretz makes בגדים
bgadim טמא, tamei, it's בגדים bgadim that it's touching. אמר ליה, Amar
leh, שרץ בהדיא כתיב ביה, sheretz behedya ksiv bei, או איש אשר
יגע בכל שרץ. o ish asher yiga b'chol sheretz. No, no, no,
we don't learn that out from the שרץ's sheretz ability to be
מטמא בגדים, metamei bgadim, it's an explicit פסוק. pasuk. אלא שכבת זרע.
Ella shichvas zera.
Okay fine, how about semen? דמטמא אדם מנלן? D'metamei adam menalan? How
do you know that if somebody touches semen they become טמא, tamei,
which is actually not true whatever, לאו משום דהוא מטמא בגדים מטמא
אדם? lav mishum d'hu metamei bgadim metamei adam? It must be because
it's מטמא בגדים, metamei bgadim, it makes בגדים bgadim טמא, tamei, so
if it's on a person it makes a person טמא. tamei. So
again we can make this equation from בגדים bgadim to a
person. אמר ליה, Amar leh, שכבת זרע נמי בהדיא כתיב ביה. shichvas
zera nami behedya ksiv bei. It's not that we learn a person
from בגדים, bgadim, it's an explicit verse. או איש, O ish, or
a person,
אשר תצא ממנו שכבת זרע asher tetzei mimenu shichvas zera is the
verse, who actually has an emission, but here we're learning it out
even someone who touches
semen, לרבות את הנוגע, l'rabos es hanogea, to include somebody who touches.
So just because something, so you cannot infer that because a, what
do you call it, a מצורע metzora makes his בגדים bgadim טמא
tamei that he would also make a person טמא. tamei. א, Aleph,
because he's wearing his בגדים bgadim so that has a different status
and other cases of the תורה Torah where something makes בגדים bgadim
טמא tamei and makes a person טמא tamei are א, aleph, might
be cases where they're not being worn, and ב, beis, we might
have an explicit פסוק. pasuk. So you can't learn it out from
any of that. So the Gemara says, okay, so אהדר ליה בבדיחותא.
ahadar leh b'vidichusa. So this was, who was it that was asking
Rav Sheshes this question? I forgot. Rav Achtivoi was asking Rav Sheshes
this question. And every time Rav Sheshes tried to come up with
an answer, Rav Achtivoi, as we would say in yeshivish language, shlugged
him up, okay. So, "That's not an answer, that's not an answer,"
and sometimes it was actually an explicit
פסוק, pasuk, okay. So he laughed a little, like, you know, maybe
he wasn't intentionally trying to make fun, but he like, you know,
laughed, "What type of answer is that? I thought it was a
חזון," chazon, you know, so he laughed a little bit at Rav
Sheshes or responding to Rav
Sheshes. חלש דעתיה דרב ששת, Chalash datei d'Rav Sheshes, so Rav Sheshes
felt very despondent, despairing, ah he's making fun of me. אישתיק רב
אחטיבוי בר אמי. Ishtik Rav Achtivoi bar Ami. So this would be
like a better outcome, because sometimes when a rabbi feels despondent because
he feels someone's making fun of him, the person dies. So it's
not the case here. Here Rav Achtivoi only now became mute. He
became unable to speak, which is a more מידה כנגד מידה mida
k'neged mida I guess, but okay. ואישתכח תלמודיה, V'ishtakach talmudei, but now
worse than that, or maybe also מידה כנגד מידה, mida k'neged mida,
he lost all of his learning. He forgot all his learning. Okay,
אתא אימיה, Ata imei, so Rav Achtivoi's, now the question is whose
mother is this? Rashi says it's Rav Sheshes's mother, Tosfos says it's
Rav Achtivoi's mother. So let's say Rav Sheshes's mother came, וקא בכיא
קמיה, v'ka bachya kamei, was crying to Rav Sheshes, imploring on behalf
of this other rabbi. And she said, צווחא צווחא ולא אשגח בה,
tzavcha tzavcha v'lo ashgach bah,
cried and cried and he didn't respond. So, and he said... System.
חזי להני חדיי chazi l'hanei chadi see my breast דמצית מנייהו d'matzit
mineihu
that you suckled from them. So you should have רחמנות. rachmanus. So
now of course it doesn't make so much sense. On one hand
it sounds like it's his mother because she's saying you suckled from
me. On the other hand, the fact that there's this all this
nurturing or whatever makes more sense that it's רב אחבוי's Rav Achavai
mother. So תוספות Tosfos says it's רב אחבוי's Rav Achavai mother who
was רב ששת's Rav Sheshes nursemaid when he was—this really makes it
much more personal.
So how can you do this to my son? Okay. So it
says fine. So בעי רחמי עליה ואיתסי. bei rachamei alei v'itassi. He
prayed for him and he was healed. Okay, so now anyway so
that's why he's called the suckling who perverts the path of the
mother. Okay, that's why that was that name שותה ששבשי. shotei sheshabshei.
Some person smarter than me will explain how this is connected to
our צדקה tzedakah discussion right now it seems like it's just a
digression. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Now, ודהא אתן
עלה. v'da'ataun aleh. Now, while we were—the thing that we were talking
about, let's, you know, let's finish up our digression before getting back
to צדקה. tzedakah. You raise a good question: מנלן, menalan, how do
you know that a מצורע metzora is מטמא אדם? metamei adam? כדתניא—רבי
שמעון בן יוחאי says, נאמר כיבוס בגדים בימי ספורו ונאמר כיבוס בגדים
בימי חלוטו. ne'emar kibus begadim bimei sipuro v'ne'emar kibus begadim bimei chaluto.
It speaks about washing his garments that you have to purify his
garments at this period of ספורו sipuro after the purification process was
done and it speaks about it during the time when he's still
like all locked up, you know, when he's still in his greatest
טומאה tumah status. מה להלן מטמא אדם אף כאן מטמא אדם—the mah
lehalan metamei adam af kan metamei adam same way—so it connects the
two. So the same way at that earlier status we know the
מצורע metzora is מטמא אדם, metamei adam, אף כאן מטמא אדם af
kan metamei adam here too during this status as well. Fine. All
right. That was all a fascinating complicated digression. Moving back, coming back.
אמר רבי אלעזר. amar Rabbi Elazar. גדול—I'm Gadol sorry, אמר רבי אלעזר
גדול עושה צדקה בסתר יותר ממשה רבינו. amar Rabbi Elazar gadol oseh
tzedakah b'seser yoser miMoshe Rabbeinu. A person who gives צדקה tzedakah in,
in private, you know, without other people knowing about it, is greater
than משה רבינו. Moshe Rabbeinu. Now that's a pretty huge statement. So
תוספות Tosfos says גדול עושה בסתר, gadol oseh b'seser, if you look
at תוספות, Tosfos, גדול ממשה רבינו, gadol miMoshe Rabbeinu, תוספות Tosfos says
פירוש יותר משכך חמה ממשה רבינו בתפלתו. peirush yoser meshachach cheimah miMoshe
Rabbeinu bitfilaso. It has more power to calm down God's anger than
משה Moshe could in his prayers. It doesn't mean you become greater
than משה רבינו. Moshe Rabbeinu. Okay, so anyway let's take a look.
דאילו במשה רבינו כתיב כי יגורתי מפני האף והחמה. d'ilu b'Moshe Rabbeinu
kesiv ki yagorti mipnei ha'af v'hacheimah. I was fearful from God's anger
and wrath. Okay, so משה Moshe could not counter God's anger and
wrath, he was afraid of it. ואילו בעושה צדקה כתיב מתן בסתר
יכפה אף. v'ilu b'oseh tzedakah kesiv matan b'seser yichpeh af. When it
comes to giving צדקה tzedakah it says מתן בסתר, matan b'seser, a
gift in private, you know, without anybody knowing about it, has the
power to cover up the anger, the wrath. ושחד בחיק חמה עזה.
v'shochad becheik cheimah azah. And now שוחד shochad we know means bribery,
but here it means the giving of money like, you know, again
off, like in the—it means in the, you know, in the bosom,
meaning like, you know, in private just between people, not out in
public, you know, also, you know, calms down a very fiery anger,
strong anger. So it's more powerful, it's able to stand up to
what משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu couldn't stand up to. Is that the
connection to the story above? You think? Okay,
what? בחיק. becheik. בחיק. becheik. I was thinking about that, but I'm
not sure
בחיק becheik and whatever. Anyway, maybe. ופליגא דרבי יצחק. u'pliga d'Rabbi Yitzchak.
It argues with רבי יצחק. Rabbi Yitzchak. דאמר רבי יצחק אף כופה
חמה אינו כופה. d'amar Rabbi Yitzchak af kofeh cheimah eino kofeh. The
word יכפה, yichpeh, to like cover up and protect from, is only
by the word אף. af. It's only by the word anger. Now
of course, you know, you think that it's anger and the strong
fiery, you know, חמה, cheimah, but he actually splits the פסוק pasuk
in two. No, no. צדקה tzedakah just protects from the אף, af,
from the anger, but not from the חמה עזה, cheimah azah, not
from the
fiery—I need another word for anger. Okay, but not from the חמה.
cheimah. Rage, fierce, fierce rage. Okay. So אף כופה חמה אינו כופה.
af kofeh cheimah eino kofeh. שנאמר ושחד בחיק חמה עזה. shene'emar v'shochad
becheik cheimah azah. אף על פי ששוחד בחיק. af al pi sheshochad
becheik. That's a different part of the פסוק. pasuk. Even with that
giving in private, חמה עזה, cheimah azah, if God really has that
fiery anger, even צדקה tzedakah won't stand up against it. ואיכא דאמרי
אמר רבי יצחק כל הנותן שוחד מביא חמה עזה לעולם. v'ika d'amri
amar Rabbi Yitzchak kol hanosein shochad meivi cheimah azah l'olam. Restoring a
more, you know, an earlier meaning of the word שוחד. shochad. Any,
any judge who takes bribe brings fiery anger to the world. שנאמר
ושחד בחיק חמה עזה. shene'emar v'shochad becheik cheimah azah. Really reading this
as two,
as two totally separate things: one about צדקה tzedakah and one about
bribery. ואמר רבי יצחק כל הנותן פרוטה לעני מתברך בשש ברכות. v'amar
Rabbi Yitzchak kol hanosein prutah l'ani misbarech b'sheish brachos. Anybody who gives
a, you know, a nickel to a, a penny to an עני
ani is blessed with six blessings. But והמפייסו בדברים, v'hamifayaso bidvarim, if
you're able to just use your words to make him feel better—okay,
he's a very important pastoral counseling גמרא Gemara or
whatever—you know, money is good, okay, but if you can actually speak
to his נשמה neshamah and console and make him feel better, you
know, then it's
מתברך באחת עשרה ברכות, misbarech b'achas esrei brachos, with eleven blessings. הנותן
פרוטה לעני מתברך בשש ברכות. hanosein prutah l'ani misbarech b'sheish brachos. דכתיב
הלא פרוס לרעב לחמך. d'kesiv halo faros lara'ev lachmecha. That's about your
לחם, lechem, your bread. And
it speaks ועניים מרודים תביא בית, v'aniyim merudim tavi bayis, כי תראה
ערום וכסיתו. ki sireh arom v'chisiso. אז יבקע כשחר אורך, az yibaka
kashachar orecha, that's one, והלך לפניך צדקך, v'halach l'fanecha tzidkecha, three, וכבוד
ה' יאספך, v'chvod Hashem ya'asfecha, four, אז תקרא וה' יענה, az tikra
v'Hashem ya'aneh, five, תשוע ויאמר הנני, tishava v'yomar hineni, okay, so that's
six. Good, thank you ב"ח. Bach. Okay, והמפייסו בדברים, v'hamifayes bidvarim, but
he actually,
you know, sort of support him with your words, מתברך בי"א ברכות,
misparech b'achas esrei brachos, with eleven. שנאמר, shene'emar,
ותפק לרעב נפשך, v'safek lara'ev nafshecha, you sort of extend to the
hungry your soul, you don't just extend money, you extend your soul
to the person, ונפש נענה תשביע, v'nefesh na'ana tasbia, and you satisfy
the soul of the person, again reading נפש nefesh you could read
נפש nefesh as being like, you know, the hunger or the person
or whatever, but here it's reading it as the soul. You address
the needs of the soul, you give sustenance to that.
Then וזרח בחשך
אורך, v'zarach bachoshech orecha, that's two, ואפלתך כצהרים, v'afailascha katzohorayim, three, ונחך
ה' תמיד, v'nachacha Hashem tamid, four, והשביע בצחצחות נפשך, v'hisbia b'tzachtzachos nafshecha,
four, and the ב"ח Bach gives the rest.
Okay, ובנו ממך חרבות עולם, ubanu mimcha chorvos olam, five, מוסדי דור
ודור תקומם, moseidi dor vador t'komem, six, and there are five more.
Okay, ואמר רב יהודה בר מרמיא, v'amar Rav Yehuda bar Meramya, what?
I think this is הפטרות Haftarot on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Yes,
it is. Yes, absolutely. By the way, look at this תוספות, Tosafot,
והמפייסו בדברים מתברך בי"א. v'hamifayes bidvarim misparech b'yud aleph. יש מגיהים והנותן
פרוטה לעני ומפייסו. yesh magihim v'hanosein pruta l'ani umfayeso.
They want to have it, no, no, no, it's not enough just
to support him, if you give him money and you support him.
משום דמשמע ליתרי קראי והנותן צדקה דכתיב ותפק לרעב נפשך ונפש נענה
תשביע. mishum d'mashma liyisrei krayi v'hanosein tzedaka dichsiv v'safek lara'ev nafshecha v'nefesh
na'ana tasbia. ולאו מילתא היא. v'lav milsa hi. דנפש נענה תשביע d'nefesh
na'ana tasbia when it says that you satiate the soul of the
oppressed, היינו תשביע בדברים שמפייסו בדברים, hainu tasbia bidvarim shemifaysehu bidvarim, it
doesn't mean with food. You satiate it with words, right, you give
sustenance. וגרסינן ליה דצדקה. v'garsinan lei d'tzadaka. So he says no, just
pure speaking without giving any money if you're able to provide support
is more powerful than, you know, eleven, twice as powerful as giving
money. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, and
that was a very important sort of balance to the emphasis all
about the צדקה tzedaka money about this obviously other critical other component.
Okay, ואמר רבי אלעזר מאי דכתיב, v'amar Rabbi Elazar mai dichsiv, what's
meant by the verse רודף צדקה וחסד ימצא חיים צדקה וכבוד? rodeif
tzedaka v'chesed yimtza chayim tzedaka v'chavod? The one who runs after צדקה
tzedaka and חסד chesed will find life, צדקה, tzedaka, and honor. משום
דרודף צדקה ימצא צדקה? mishum d'rodeif tzedaka yimtza tzedaka? Because you run
after צדקה tzedaka you find צדקה? tzedaka? Again reading צדקה tzedaka here
as charity. So if רודף צדקה rodeif tzedaka means you're running to
give charity, and then you will find charity... but wait, that's not
a ברכה. bracha. I don't want to be needing charity from other
people. Okay, so I don't think צדקה tzedaka means charity. I know
it doesn't, I said at the beginning of the day. No, but
I mean even giving money. I know. So now we're going to
have a discussion which I agree to, which is that charity is
a Christian word which reflects the sense of like it is a
just an act that is not deserved or warranted, it's like a
חסד chesed element, right? And צדקה tzedaka because it's rooted in the
word of צדק tzedek to emphasize more of a sense of the
justice of doing that, a hundred percent. But in the past when
I've tried to use other words other than charity like alms, people
said that was more Christian. So you can come up with some
other word or we don't have to translate it and we'll just
call it צדקה. tzedaka. But you are right to note that charity
is a Christian concept, the word charity and what it suggests. Okay,
anyway, so משום דרודף צדקה ימצא צדקה? mishum d'rodeif tzedaka yimtza tzedaka?
אלא לומר לך כל הרודף אחר צדקה הקדוש ברוך הוא ממציא לו
ממון לעשות בהן צדקה. ella lomar lach kol harodeif achar tzedaka Hakadosh
Baruch Hu mamtzi lo mammon l'asos bahen tzedaka. No, no,
no, if you give צדקה tzedaka then הקדוש ברוך הוא Hakadosh Baruch
Hu will, you know, will reward you with more money to enable
to give more צדקה. tzedaka. רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר הקדוש ברוך
הוא ממציא לו בני אדם המהוגנים לעשות בהן צדקה. Rav Nachman bar
Yitzchak amar Hakadosh Baruch Hu mamtzi lo bnei adam hamehuganim l'asos bahen
tzedaka. No,
no, no, it just means that if you're looking to give צדקה,
tzedaka, הקדוש ברוך הוא Hakadosh Baruch Hu will help you give צדקה
tzedaka in a way that is meaningful, like in a way that
actually is purposeful, that the people who come to you asking for
צדקה tzedaka will be people who really deserve it, כדי לקבל עליהם
שכרם, kidei lekabel aleihem scharo, in order that you should receive proper
reward. לאפוקי מאי? l'afukei mai? What's this exclude? לאפוקי מדדרש רבא דדרש
רבא. l'afukei midrash Rava d'darash Rava. רבא Rava explicated: מאי דכתיב ויהיו
מוכשולים לפניך. mai dichsiv v'yiyu michshalim l'fanecha.
This is when ירמיהו Yirmiyahu was talking to God angry about all
the people that were always attacking him. He said let them be
stumble in your presence, בעת אפך עשה בהם, b'eis apecha asei bahem,
act against them at the time of your anger. אמר ירמיהו לפני
הקדוש ברוך הוא, amar Yirmiyahu lifnei Hakadosh Baruch Hu, ירמיהו Yirmiyahu said
to God, ריבונו של עולם אפילו בשעה שכופין את יצרם ומבקשים לעשות
צדקה לפניך, Ribono shel Olam afilu b'sha'as shekovin es yitzram umvakeshim l'asos
tzedaka l'fanecha,
even when they're trying to do מצוות, mitzvos, okay, I guess that's
the לפניך, l'fanecha, they're trying to act and doing מצוות, mitzvos, הכשילם,
hachshilem, you should הכשילם, hachshilem, right, מוכשולים, michshalim, בבני אדם שאינם מהוגנים,
bivnei adam she'einam mehuganim,
with people that are not deserving. So even when they're trying to
do מצוות, mitzvos, you should subvert their intent, make sure that the
people asking them for charity don't deserve the charity and then they
won't get שכר schar for doing their מצווה. mitzvah. כדי שלא יקבלו
עליהם שכר, kidei shelo yekablu aleihem schar,
which points to obviously, you know, the interesting point about like yes,
you know, all this emphasis
about
giving.
No, לאפוקי le'apukei. *la'apukei* doesn't mean it disagrees with it. It means
to sort of like, you know, as opposed to the scenario described
by. He was describing a scenario that you wind up giving to
wrong people. You'll be rewarded by giving to the right people. Sorry,
okay, right. Now, I do need to say though, you know, we're
going to get into a little interesting question here. Like the phrase
of, let me give it to the right person so I can
get שכר *schar* for what I'm doing. It almost, it almost makes
the poor person like my לולב *lulav*, okay? I'm using them to
do my מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* to get שכר *schar*. And so let's
just keep that in mind as we continue, okay? So, okay. רבי
יהושע בן לוי אומר כל הרגיל לעשות צדקה tzedakah זוכה שיהיו לו
בנים banim. בעלי חכמה chochma, בעלי עושר בעלי אגדה *Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi omer kol haragil la'asot tzedakah zocheh
sheyihyu lo banim ba'alei chochmah ba'alei osher ba'alei agadah*. So here's interesting
also about bridging that gap, right? Because here you're encouraging all people
to give צדקה tzedakah. *tzedakah*, which is something that's accessible to the
masses, right? And but how, but you know, what do you do
in a society where still like, you know, rabbinic achievement, Torah achievement
is the greatest social status, the greatest religious achievement? So what it
says is if you're really good at giving צדקה tzedakah *tzedakah*, maybe
you're not going to be a תלמיד חכם *talmid chacham*, okay? You're
a wealthy person, a philanthropist, but you'll be זוכה *zocheh* and you'll
have your kids who are תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim, *talmidei chachamim*. זוכה
שיהיו לו בנים בעלי חכמה בעלי עושר *zocheh sheyihyu lo banim ba'alei
chochmah ba'alei osher*. Also they'll be wealthy, okay, so best of both
worlds, okay, and בעלי אגדה *ba'alei agadah*. And they'll also be good
at דרשן *darshan*. בעלי חכמה דכתיב ימצא חיים *ba'alei chochmah d'ichtiv yimtza
chayim*. Okay, so this is going back to the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*,
right? רודף צדקה tzedakah וחסד ימצא חיים צדקה tzedakah. וכבוד *rodef tzedakah
v'chesed yimtza chayim tzedakah v'chavod*. So חיים *chayim*, that's life. Life is
Torah like Rashi says. If you look at Rashi, דכתיב גבי חכמה
כי מוצאי מצא חיים *d'ichtiv gabei chochmah ki motzai matza chayim*. Okay,
so that's life, is Torah wisdom. בעלי עושר דכתיב צדקה tzedakah. *ba'alei
osher d'ichtiv tzedakah*. Okay, which means like before, like they'll be philanthropists
as well and also able to be בעלי צדקה tzedakah. *ba'alei tzedakah*.
בעלי אגדה דכתיב וכבוד *ba'alei agadah d'ichtiv v'chavod*. Honor. Why כבוד *chavod*?
So look at this great Rashi. Important for rabbis, or training to
be, people training to be rabbis. בעלי אגדה מתוך שהם דרשנים ומושכים
את הלב הכל מכבדים אותם *ba'alei agadah mitoch shehem darshanim u'moshchim et
halev hakol mechabdim otam*. If you're a good orator, okay, which is
a different skill than being a תלמיד חכם *talmid chacham*, if you're
a good orator, you get a lot of public recognition. All right,
so that's בעלי כבוד *ba'alei kavod*. כתיב הכא וכבוד וכתיב התם U'chtiv
hatam, כבוד חכמים ינחלו *ktiv hacha v'chavod u'ktiv hatam kavod chachamim yinchalu*.
Okay, but it's also an honor of sages. It's an honor coming
through teaching Torah still. Okay, תניא *tanya*. It's a ברייתא braita, *braita*.
היה רבי מאיר אומר יש לו לבעל הדין להשיבך ולומר לך *hayah
Rabbi Meir
omer yesh lo l'ba'al hadin l'hashivcha v'lomar lacha*. The opposing party can
say to you, meaning is it your own יצר הרע *yetzer hara*,
the non-Jew, a rational argument against, you know, this. Sometimes יש לבעל
הדין *yesh l'ba'al hadin* is sort of like דע מה שתשיב לאפיקורוס
*da mah shetashiv l'apikores* type of a thing, but you know, it's
like you yourself might want to ask yourself this question. So here's
the challenge to this idea of צדקה tzedakah. *tzedakah*. ולומר לך אם
אלהיכם אוהב עניים הוא מפני מה אינו מפרנסם *v'lomar lacha im elokeichem
ohev aniyim hu mipnei mah eino mefarnesam*. But the point says your
God, sounds like we're talking about like a non-Jew, a critique from
the non-Jew. If your God truly loves the poor, מפני מה אינו
מפרנסם *mipnei mah eino mefarnesam*, let Him take care of them. The
fact that they're poor shows that they're not in God's favor. Now
this, by the way, was a very widespread theology in the ancient
world, which is the people that are wealthy clearly are the righteous
because the gods are showing them their favor, and those that are
poor are clearly the sinners, because, you know, as a reflection. Now
you could say that that's a, I use the plural obviously because
it was a pagan theology. But you know, to some degree, the
Torah talks about it, if you do the good things, ונתתי גשמיכם
בעתם *v'natati gishmeichem b'itam* etc. But it never got to that point,
first of all that was at a collective level, it never got
to that point that we think that somebody who's wealthy is necessarily
a צדיק *tzaddik* and somebody who's poor is necessarily like a רשע
rasha *rasha*. But this is the critique. צדיק וטוב לו רשע ורע
לו *tzaddik v'tov lo rasha v'ra lo*. Well that's in the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*, right, but I'm talking about like even in the biblical,
in the תנ"ך *Tanakh* theology, where it is more direct שכר ועונש
*schar v'onesh*, it never got to the point where you look at
somebody's wealth in the world and you assume that tells you whether
they're a צדיק *tzaddik* or a רשע *rasha*. But in the ancient
world, in the pagan world, there definitely was a strong theology about
that, okay? And therefore that's the critique. That we shouldn't give צדקה
tzedakah, *tzedakah*, clearly God doesn't like them. Okay? So the rich get
richer and the poor get poorer. Exactly, the rationalization. Right, well that's
also true, okay? So, אמור לו *emor lo*, say back to this
challenger, כדי שניצול אנו בהם מדינה של גיהנם *kdei shenitzol anu bahem
midina shel geihinnom*. No, God is just giving us an opportunity to
get, to be saved from גיהנם *geihinnom* that we get to do
the מצוה mitzvah. *mitzvah*. So that's a real thing about using them
as a means to do a מצוה mitzvah. *mitzvah* for us. Oh
yeah, God did this so that we could get rewarded. Okay, yeah,
yeah, maybe to even say, yeah, yeah, maybe they don't deserve where
they are, you know, I mean, maybe they aren't righteous, maybe they
don't deserve the money, but it gives us an opportunity. It's a
little bit, sounds like that.
Okay, וזו שאלה שאל טורנוסרופוס Turnusrufus הרשע *v'zu she'elah she'al Turnusrufus harasha*.
Now we're going to see a slightly different version of this. You
know, Turnusrufus, who was the sort of governor of the Land of
Israel in the time of רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*, so he asked
את רבי עקיבא *et Rabbi Akiva*, אלהיכם אוהב עניים הוא *elokeichem ohev
aniyim hu*. So the exact same language. language if your God loves
the poor מפני מה אינו מפרנסם let him take care of them.
So אמר ליה amar lei כדי שננצל בהן מדינא של גיהנום. kedei
she-ninatzel ba-hen mi-dina shel Gehennom. No they're it's in order that we
should be able to do מצוות. mitzvot. אמר ליה amar lei אדרבה
adaraba זו שמחייבתן לגיהנום. zu she-mechayvatan le-Gehennom.
This is making you more sinful. You're giving to people that God
has shown God doesn't want them to have money. אמשול לך משל
emshol lecha mashal let me give you a משל. mashal. למה הדבר
דומה le-mah ha-davar domeh למלך בשר ודם le-melech basar va-dam שקעס על
עבדו she-ka_as al avdo an earthly king got mad at his servant
וחבשו בבית האסורים ve-chavsho be-veit ha-asurim and locked him up in jail
וציווה עליו שלא להאכילו ושלא להשקותו ve-tzivah alav she-lo le-ha_akhilo ve-she-lo le-hashkoto
and told everybody don't feed him don't give him food and drink.
והלך אדם אחד והאכילו והשקהו ve-halakh adam echad ve-he_ekhilo ve-hishkahu and somebody
came and subverted the contradictory message the ruling of the king and
gave him food and drink. כששמע המלך לא כועס עליו? keshe-shama ha-melech
lo ko_es alav? If the king is going to hear that person
will be punished. ואתם קרויים עבדים ve-atem keruyim avadim and you're slaves
to God שנאמר כי לי בני ישראל עבדים עבדי הם. she-ne_emar ki
li venei Yisrael avadim avadai hem. Turnusrufus really knew his פסוקים. pesukim.
Anyway so you're violating the divine decree. The divine decree I see
as the way the world is as the way God wants it.
So you're subverting obviously the similar type of things the fact that
we do a ברית מילה berit milah subvert the natural order of
the world. There's a natural order of the world the poor is
this you're subverting that natural order that's going against the will of
God. Of course saying that God wants it that way and said
not to feed him when there's מצוות mitzvot in the תורה Torah
to take care of the poor is pretty ironic because it's obviously
God anyway. But Rabbi Akiva answers him within this mindset without quoting
the פסוקים pesukim that we have מצוות mitzvot to do it. So
אמר לו רבי עקיבא amar lo Rabbi Akiva Rabbi Akiva said to
him אמשול לך משל למה הדבר דומה emshol lecha mashal le-mah ha-davar
domeh למלך בשר ודם שקעס על בנו. le-melech basar va-dam she-ka_as al
beno. I'll give you a משל mashal except it's his son that
he's angry at. שקעס על בנו she-ka_as al beno וחבשו בבית האסורים
וציווה עליו שלא להאכילו ושלא להשקותו ve-chavsho be-veit ha-asurim ve-tzivah alav she-lo
le-ha_akhilo ve-she-lo le-hashkoto והלך אדם אחד והאכילו והשקהו ve-halakh adam echad ve-he_ekhilo
ve-hishkahu just like you said except it's the son who's in prison.
So even though the king said don't feed him it's because the
king had to act that way for
to protect his status or to teach the son a lesson but
obviously he really wants the son taken care of. All right so
כששמע המלך לא דורון משגר לו? keshe-shama ha-melech lo doron meshageir lo?
The king is going to send a gift to this person who
managed to find a way to support his son. Okay so which
is interesting that's a little bit buying into the mentality. It's sort
of like a לשיטתך. le-shitatkha. Even if we think they're poor because
to some degree they did something wrong and they deserve to be
punished ultimately God cares about everyone and we're God's children and we
God really wants us at the same time that maybe they somewhat
deserve
this. I'm saying that's a little bit of a subtext we have
to have a מצוה mitzvah. to try to take care of them.
So here צדקה tzedakah and love actually come very close together. Well
that's true and that's a good point it's more the charity idea
a bit. ואנן קרויים בנים ve-anan keruyim banim and we're God's children
not just God's slaves דכתיב בנים אתם לה' אלהיכם. de-khetiv banim atem
la-Hashem Elokeichem. אמר לו amar lo so he said back to him
אתם קרויים בנים וקרויים עבדים. atem keruyim banim ve-keruyim avadim. Let's figure
out which one is the פלוגתא. plugta. We got a פסוק pasuk
that says one a פסוק pasuk. that says the other סתירה. stira.
So this is what Turnusrufus says בזמן שאתם עושים רצונו של מקום
אתם קרויים בנים. be-zman she-atem osim retzono shel Makom atem keruyim banim.
When you're doing God's will you're God's children. בזמן שאין אתם עושים
רצונו של מקום אתם קרויים עבדים. be-zman she-ein atem osim retzono shel
Makom atem keruyim avadim. Now
which are you nowadays? Well if you want to look at the
natural order of things you're under Roman rule so that clearly shows
you're not in God's favor. ועכשיו אין אתם עושים רצונו של מקום.
ve-akhshav ein atem osim retzono shel Makom. So clearly you're not in
God's favor so you shouldn't be supporting the poor. אמר לו amar
lo הרי הוא אומר harei hu omer now we caught a פסוק.
pasuk. Before your argument ends by the natural order I got a
פסוק. pasuk הלא פרוס לרעב לחמך ועניים מרודים תביא בית. halo faros
la-ra_ev lachmekha ve-aniyim merudim tavi vayit. אימתי? eimatai?
Now. Not only is it just a פסוק pasuk. but it also
addresses your argument of even when we're at a time of disfavor
this is our obligation. אימתי עניים מרודים תביא בית? eimatai aniyim merudim
tavi vayit? When do you bring the outcast poor into your house?
האידנא ha-idna nowadays. Now
it's not exactly clear. If you remember yesterday we also caught this
phrase עניים מרודים aniyim merudim which the גמרא Gemara somehow understood it
to mean when the non-Jewish tax collectors the Roman tax collectors are
coming to take money from you to support the poor. So somehow
this phrase עניים מרודים aniyim merudim refers to nowadays when people when
you are actually demanding and entering into our house as it were
and demanding our צדקה. tzedakah. So that's nowadays. And even though that's
the reality we're under your subjection דקאמר הלא פרוס לרעב לחמך de-ka_amar
halo faros la-ra_ev lachmekha we still have to support the poor. Which
is interesting which is at the end of the day so what
is the theological response? The theological response is basically like what we're
still בנים. And that yes maybe this natural order like לשיטתך le-shitatkha
indicates a certain degree of God's displeasure but we're still God's children
and therefore God really wants us at the same time to respond
with compassion to... All right. Also to point to the return. In
other words by doing it then we can get this forgiveness. Get
back right exactly.
Okay. דרש רב יהודה ברבי שלום darash Rav Yehuda beribi Shalom שכשם
שמזונותיו של אדם קצובים לו מראש השנה she-keshem she-mezonotav shel adam ketzuvim
lo me-Rosh ha-Shanah the same way and by the way I'll just
say one last thing about that that therefore even the sort of
sense of using the עני ani to get reward might have only
been like
in לשיטתך le-shitatkha of Turnusrufus within your theology I'll explain it. So
yes, maybe within your theology they're not deserving, but we still have
this מצוה. mitzvah. And we use, and by giving it, we get
reward. It doesn't mean that the rabbis really believed that, you know,
you see צדקה tzedakah, as a means for you to get a
מצוה. mitzvah, Okay, you know, to use the עני ani in that
way. Okay, so let's keep on going. Okay, כשם שמזונותיו של אדם
קצובים לו מראש השנה כך חסרונותיו של אדם קצובים לו מראש השנה.
keshem shemezonotav shel adam ketsuvim lo me-Rosh Hashanah kach chesronotav shel adam
ketsuvim lo me-Rosh Hashanah. The same way it's determined how much income
you'll make in the year, it's also determined how much money you
will spend in the course of the year. All right, so you
could not just say tell me my net, but no, no, two
things are determined: your gross income and your expenses and how much
money is leaving your bank account. Now, why is that relevant? זכה
הלא פרוס לרעב לחמך. zakha halo feros lara'av lakhmecha. If you merit,
that amount that was decreed that you should have to spend this
year is going to go to support the poor. You'll do מצות
mitzvot with it. You know, you'll use it to help other people
and you'll get this מצוה. לא זכה ועניים מרודים תביא בית. lo
zakha va'aniyim merudim tavi bayit.
Again, that means somehow the Romans are going to enter into your
house and they'll take that money as well. So that money is
going to be taken to, you know, to support the poor, but
are you going to give it or somebody going to take it
from you? כי הא, ki ha, like the story of the בני
אחתיה דרבי יוחנן בן זכאי, benei achateih de-Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai, the
sons of the daughter of רבי יוחנן בן זכאי. Rabbi Yochanan ben
Zakkai. חזא להו בחלמא דבעו למיחסר שבע מאה דינרי. chaza lehu bechelma
devau lemichsar sheva me'ah dinarei. He saw in a dream that that
coming year they were going to lose 700 dinars. עשינהו, asinhu, the
word עשינהו asinhu from the word again גדול המעשה יותר מן העושה.
gadol hama'aseh yoter min ha'oseh.
The word עושה oseh in the context of צדקה tzedakah, is and
מעשה ma'aseh means to make somebody give צדקה. tzedakah Okay, so it's
a very interesting word. עשינהו, asinhu, he sort of, you know, made
them give צדקה. tzedakah, He over the course of the year, various
times made appeals to them and asked them to give צדקה. tzedakah
And over the course of the year, שקל מינייהו לצדקה, shakal mineihu
litzedakah, and he took from them for צדקה. tzedakah פוש בהו שיבסר
דינרי. push behu shivasar dinarei. At the end of the year, there
was only 17 dinars left of the 700 that they had. Now
they were unaware of this dream or anything. Just over the course
of the year, he kept on going to them and asking them,
we have this, you know, we're collecting for this, we're collecting for
that. And over the course of the year, they had given 600
and whatever it is, 83 dinars. Only minus 17 from the total.
כי מטא מעלי יומא דכיפורי, ki mata ma'alei yoma de-Kippuri, when ערב
יום כיפור Erev Yom Kippur came about, שדרו דבי קיסר נקטינהו. shaddaru
de-bei keisar naktinhu. So finally Rashi says the dream was מוצאי יום
כיפור, Motza'ei Yom Kippur, so it's now a full year later. It's
the end of the year, right? I guess what's decreed about you
is going to happen on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So and now
the דבי קיסר de-bei keisar have sent and demanded 17 dinars for
some, you know, for their own purposes, for the government's purposes. Okay,
so now the full 700 was given.
So, where was it?
אמר להו, amar lehu, so רבי יוחנן בן זכאי Rabbi Yochanan ben
Zakkai said to them, לא תדחלו, lo tidchalu, don't be afraid that
the government might take more. שיבסר דינרי
דגבייכו שקלינהו מינייכו. shivasar dinarei degavaichu shaklinhu mineichu. The 17 that were
still, you know, decreed to have to give, that was what they
took from you. They're not going to take from you anymore. That
makes the total of 700. So you see that if you don't
give it on your own for צדקה, tzedakah, the government is going
to come and take it. So you might as well give it
on your own. So אמרו ליה מנא ידעת, amru leih mana yadata,
how do you know that we were going to give 700 over
the course of the year, that it was that there only had
17 or whatever? אמר להו חלמא חזאי לכו amar lehu chelma chazai
lachon because I saw this in a dream.
אמרו ליה ואמאי לא אמרת לן, amru leih ve'amai lo amart lan,
why didn't you tell us a year ago? דנסיבנהו, denasibinhu, then we
would have happily given you the 700 because we would have known
we had to give it and we were going to lose it
anyway, might as well given it to you. אמר להו אמינא כי
היכי דתעבדו מצוה
לשמה. amar lehu amina ki heichi detabdu mitzvah lishmah. That's obviously the
answer. I wanted you to give it for the sake of מצוה.
I didn't want you to give it out of a mentality that,
oh, we're going to lose this money anyway, better we should give
it than the government take it. Give it from a sense that
you're not going to lose it and you still want to give
it. Of course, the irony is that by teaching this, what's sort
of the message? If we really hear
this story and internalize it, we're going to say, oh, I should
give a lot of money to צדקה Tzedakah? because probably, you know,
there's a certain amount of money that's going to be I'm going
to lose over the course of the year anyway, so might as
well give it to צדקה. Tzedakah I never know exactly how much
it'll be. So it sort of introduces a little element of שלא
לשמה shelo lishmah in our giving. But since we're sort of like
between the two extremes, we don't have the dream, we don't know
exactly how much it's decreed we're going to give, but we're not
ignorant of the fact that there's this type of a calculus going
on. So it gives us a little maybe just the right amount
of שלא לשמה shelo lishmah to encourage us to give more, I
guess you'd say. How do you deal with the like the in
ברכות Berakhot we say this that you know if for a dream
to come true there's the whole idea that you have to actually
you have to actually sort of speak it aloud right and that
until you actually speak it aloud the dream doesn't have— yeah, I
don't know, there's a lot of different גמרות gemarot about dreams. So
you know I can't I can't answer that. Okay. Yeah. Or I
could tell you I know the answer but I can't
tell you
because of the dream. Exactly. What David is referring to and all
dreams go by how they're interpreted. Right. Okay. All right. Let's go
on. Okay. רב פפא. Rav Pappa. רב פפא הוי סליק בדרגא. Rav
Papa havei salik b'darga. Now רב פפא Rav Papa was going up
on the steps. אישתמיט
כרעיה. Ishtamit kareiah. He's like leg slipped. ובעי למיפל. U'vei lemipal. He
almost fell down the steps. אמר השתא קא הוי חייב מאן דסני
לן כמחלל שבתות וכעובד עבודה זרה. Amar hashta ka havei chayav man
d'sani lan k'mechallel Shabbatot u'che'oved avodah zarah. He says, oh my God,
it almost was that the person hated to us, meaning himself, he's
saying it so as not to say something bad about himself, but
he's basically saying is, I almost fell down the steps and that
would have been a death like somebody who violates שבת Shabbos or
is an עובד עבודה זרה, oved avodah zarah, because those people get
סקילה skilah and סקילה skilah is you're thrown off a cliff. So
he's like saying like, what sin did I do that I almost
died this terrible death that indicates like a grave sin? So, אמר
ליה חייא בר רב מדיפתי לרב פפא, Amar lei Chiya bar Rav
mi-Diftei l'Rav Papa, so חייא בר רב Chiya bar Rav said to
him, שמא עני בא לידך ולא פרנסטו. Shema ani ba l'yadcha v'lo
parnastato. Maybe
a poor person came to you and you did not provide for
him. דתניא רבי יהושע בן קרחה אומר כל המעלים עיניו מן הצדקה,
D'tanya Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha omer, kol hama'alim einav min hatzedakah, anybody
who hides his eyes from giving צדקה, Tzedakah, meaning like, ignores the
עני ani in front of him, like sadly, that happens in New
York City, right? You walk down the streets and people put out
their hands and the easiest thing is like to pretend they're not
there, right? So כל המעלים עיניו מן הצדקה כאילו עובד עבודה זרה.
kol hama'alim einav min hatzedakah ke'ilu oved avodah zarah. כתיב הכא השמר
לך פן יהיה דבר עם לבבך
בליעל, K'tiv hacha, hishamer lecha pen yihyeh davar im l'vavcha beliyaal, right?
Which is to, you have this
rebellious thought to say, oh my God, the שמיטה's Shmita coming, I'm
not going to lend money to this poor person. So the decision
to ignore the poor person is this thought בליעל, beliyaal, like this
rebellious type of thought. וכתיב התם, and it says by עבודה זרה,
avodah zarah, יצאו אנשים בני בליעל. yatze'u anashim bnei beliyaal. And the
מהרש"א Maharsha points out that's the only two times in the תורה,
Torah, like in the five books of משה, Moshe, בליעל beliyaal occurs
elsewhere, that the word בליעל beliyaal is used only these two times.
מה להלן עבודה זרה אף כאן עבודה זרה. Mah halan avodah zarah,
af kan avodah zarah. Okay. So again, it's interesting, like different ways,
I mean you think about the rhetoric that we're trying to get
people to give צדקה, Tzedakah right? You give צדקה Tzedakah you'll sit
with תלמידי חכמים, you'll get all this tremendous reward. Anyway, oh, but
I can't afford it. Oh, well, the money was already pre-assigned, you're
going to lose the money anyway. If you don't do it, look
at this terrible punishment. All right, etc. Now, if you wanted to
just say one thing theologically, what's the כאילו עובד עבודה זרה, ke'ilu
oved avodah zarah, I could say, it just occurs to me, but
I think it's a nice פשט, pshat, that it sort of goes
back to the
טורנוסרופוס exchange, right? That, you know, that you are, you're sort of
accepting the natural order of things, you're accepting the sort of fate
mentality. That's כאילו עובד עבודה זרה, ke'ilu oved avodah zarah, right? So
you're not sort of seeing, and you could also sort of say
that the עבודה זרה avodah zarah is like the worship of money,
like you sort of feel like, it's all my own money, I
earned it, why should I give it? And you're ignoring the fact
that God helps you earn money. So you're sort of denying sort
of
God's participation in your own wealth. So there's a nice, I think
there's nice ways of understanding this as rather than, in addition to
just like, oh, it's a terrible thing. Okay. תניא ותנו ברייתא, Tanya,
v'tanu b'raisa, אמר רבי אלעזר ברבי יוסי כל צדקה וחסד שישראל עושים
בעולם הזה, amar Rabbi Elazar bar Rabbi Yose kol tzedakah v'chesed she'Yisrael
osim ba'olam hazeh, all righteousness and צדקה, Tzedakah or צדקה Tzedakah and
גמילות חסדים, gemilus chasadim, so, different types, again, in the rabbinic framework,
צדקה tzedakah is giving of money, and חסד chesed is the providing
of personal service and support and help and so
on. And חסד, chesed, by the way, is not limited to the
poor. All right? So anyway, כל צדקה וחסד
שישראל עושים בעולם הזה, kol tzedakah v'chesed she'Yisrael osim ba'olam hazeh, in
this world, הזה שלום גדול ופרקליטין גדולים בין ישראל לאביהם שבשמים, hazeh
shalom gadol u'peraklitin gedolim bein Yisrael l'Avihem she'ba'shamayim, will sort of stand
as, create great peace and great advocates, angels who will advocate for
you between you and your heavenly Father. שנאמר
כה אמר ה' אל תבא בית מרזח
ואל תלך לספוד ואל תנד להם. She'ne'emar, ko amar Hashem, al tavo
beit marzeach, v'al telech lispod, v'al tanud lahem. Don't go to the
house of mourning and to go to eulogize or to mourn with
them, כי אספתי את שלומי מאת העם הזה. ki asafti et shlomi
me'et ha'am hazeh. Because I have gathered up my peace, my wellbeing
from this people, את החסד ואת הרחמים. et hachesed v'et harachamim. And
so what does it mean, this is obviously a negative verse, but
God is saying I take, took my peace away from this people,
my שלום, shalom, the חסד chesed and the רחמים. rachamim. חסד זו
גמילות חסדים. Chesed, zu gemilus chasadim. That's גמילות חסדים. gemilus chasadim. רחמים
זו צדקה. Rachamim, zu tzedakah. רחמים Rachamim is צדקה, tzedakah which is
interesting, which has that sense of like
compassion, pity, it's always a sensitive thing. You want to have רחמים,
rachamim, but it's like don't treat somebody else as pathetic, right? Or
how do you have the right sort of, the right type of
רחמים, rachamim, but obviously it has to, has to speak to your
נשמה, neshamah, you have to see what this person is. I mean
I always think an important part is empathy, not necessarily sympathy. But
anyway, okay, so if God is taking His שלום shalom and He's
taking the חסד chesed and רחמים, rachamim, it means that is God's
שלום, shalom, that is what creates the שלום shalom between us and
God. תניא רבי יוסי אומר גדולה צדקה שמקרבת את הגאולה. Tanya, Rabbi
Yose omer, gedolah tzedakah she'mekarevet et hageulah. It brings close the redemption.
שנאמר כה אמר ה' שמרו משפט ועשו צדקה כי קרובה ישועתי לבוא.
She'ne'emar, ko amar Hashem shimru mishpat va'asu tzedakah ki krovah yeshuati lavo.
That will make קרובה ישועתי לבוא, krovah yeshuati lavo, וצדקתי להגלות. v'tzidkati
lhigalot. הוא היה אומר, Hu haya omer, he used to say, עשרה
דברים קשים נבראו בעולם. asarah d'varim kashim nivre'u ba'olam. There are ten
hard things. הר קשה ברזל מחתכו, Har kasheh, barzel m'chatkho, a mountain
is hard, iron cuts into it. ברזל קשה אור מפעפכו, Barzel kasheh,
ur m'papkho, iron is hard, fire melts it or whatever, makes it
bubble. אור קשה, Ur kasheh, fire is hard, so it's sort of
like a חד גדיא. chad gadya. Okay, fire and the next thing
comes and destroys. So fire is hard, מים מכבין אותה *mayim mechabin
otah*, water puts it out. מים קשין *mayim kashin*, עבין סובלים אותן
*avin sovlim otan*, water puts out fire but then the water evaporates
and clouds carry the water. עבין קשין *avin kashin*, funny word קשה
*kashe* used by clouds. Anyway, רוח מפזרתן *ruach mefazertan*, yeah but the
wind scatters them. רוח קשה *ruach kashe*, now so you have a
wind, גוף סובלו *guf sovlo*, so every body, every person is filled
with the רוח *ruach*, with a spirit, so it supports the body.
גוף קשה *guf kashe*, פחד שוברו *pachad shovro*,
now even though the body is strong, fear sort of can break,
humble you. פחד קשה *pachad kashe*, fear is hard, יין מפיגו *yayin
mefigo*, but the wine helps you deal with that anxiety, okay? Not
necessarily have to have a Surgeon General's warning there. יין קשה *yayin
kashe*, שינה מפיגתו *sheina mefigato*, wine has its effect, but you go
take a little nap or you sleep that goes away with it.
ומיתה קשה מכולם *umitah kashah mikulam*, but the worst, hardest thing is
death. וצדקה מצלת מן המיתה *utzdakah matzela min hamitah*, and tzedakah saves
from death. דכתיב וצדקה תציל ממות utzedakah tatzil mimaves. *dechtiv utzdakah tatzil
mimavet*, tzedakah will save from death. I really do not know what
the point of that was because the death thing was discontinuous with
everything else, right? Everything was really like a חד גדיא *Chad Gadya*,
this puts this out, this puts this out, and then it's this
discontinuous oh and death is the worst but צדקה tzedakah. *tzedakah* saves
you from it. So anyway, another thing is the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
that says that by שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos*, right, that death is one-sixtieth
of one-sixtieth of sleep. Oh, maybe the transition from sleep to death.
That could be, that's a nice point, good point. דרש דוסתאי ברבי
ינאי *Darsh Dostai Berabi Yannai*, בוא וראה שלא כמדת הקדוש ברוך הוא
מדת בשר ודם *bo u'rei shelo kemidat hakadosh baruch hu midat basar
vadam*, God is not like humans. אדם מביא דורון גדול למלך *adam
mevi doron gadol lemelech*, you bring a big gift to the king,
ספק מקבלין אותו הימנו ספק אין מקבלין אותו הימנו *safek mekablin oto
heimenu safek ein mekablin oto heimenu*, you don't know if the king
will accept your gift. ואם תמצי לומר מקבלין אותו הימנו ספק רואה
פני המלך ספק אינו רואה פני המלך *ve'im timtzi lomar mekablin oto
heimenu safek roeh pnei hamelech safek eino roeh pnei hamelech*, even after
he accepts it, you don't know you'll get an audience with the
king. והקדוש ברוך הוא אינו כן *vehakadosh baruch hu eino kein*, God
isn't this way. אדם נותן פרוטה לעני *adam noten pruta le'ani*, you
give a פרוטה *pruta* to a poor person, זוכה ומקבל פני השכינה
*zoche umekabel pnei hashchina*, you immediately merit an audience with God. שנאמר
*shenemar*, אני בצדק אחזה פניך *ani betzedek echezeh panecha*,
I with righteousness will see your face, your presence. So by giving
צדקה tzedakah. *tzedakah*, that will allow me to encounter God. אחזה פניך
*echezeh panecha*. מה אשבעה בהקיץ תמונתך *ma esbe'ah behakitz tmunatecha*. Now of
course what you could say is, as opposed to does oh look
you do this here's your reward, like another encouragement to do the
right thing, you could also speak about the fact about the צלם
אלקים *tzelem Elokim* in every human being. If you give צדקה tzedakah?
*tzedakah* because you really see the person in front of you and
that you're responding to that and the divinity in each person, then
that's a ראיית פני ה' *re'iat pnei HaShem*. That's an encountering of
God's presence. Like God hovering over יעקב Yaakov *Yaakov* when he's sick.
Right, so same kind of... Yeah, but that's God hovering, I'm trying
to say a little bit even more, like sometimes we don't give
because we allow ourselves to not, whatever, they're just poor, we don't
see that if we saw every person as a צלם אלקים *tzelem
Elokim* how could we not give them צדקה tzedakah *tzedakah*, right? So
maybe how could we not help them? What? Maybe connected to the
עבודה זרה *avodah zarah* aspect as well. רבי אלעזר יהיב פרוטה לעני
והדר מצלי *Rabbi Elazar yahiv pruta le'ani vehadar matzli*, רבי אלעזר *Rabbi
Elazar* would do this, he would first give a פרוטה *pruta* to
an עני ani *ani* before he would דאוון *daven* and then he
would דאוון *daven*. אמר דכתיב *amar dechtiv*, אני בצדק אחזה פניך *ani
betzedek echezeh panecha*, first I want to give צדקה *tzedakah* before I
go pray. And of course you could also read that also in
a different way as well. Before I feel I have the right
or the merit to stand before God and ask God for my
own needs, which is what the central part of שמונה עשרה *Shemoneh
Esrei* is, I have to show that I care about other people,
right? It's sort of like if you want God to care about
you, let's show you acting in a similar way, let's show you
being sensitive to other people's needs and responding to them because that's
what you're asking God to do for you. מה אשבעה בהקיץ תמונתך
*ma esbe'ah behakitz tmunatecha*, what is the end of that פסוק pasuk.
*pasuk*? I will be satiated in my wakingness your visit. אמר רבי
יוחנן אמר רבי יצחק *amar Rabbi Yochanan amar Rabbi Yitzchak*, אלו תלמידי
חכמים שמנדדין שינה מעיניהם בעולם הזה *elu talmidei chachamim shemnadedin sheina mei'eineihem
ba'olam hazeh*, that they don't get to sleep too much in this
world because they're staying up very late learning. והקדוש ברוך הוא משביען
מזיו שכינתו לעולם הבא *vehakadosh baruch hu masbi'an miziv shchinato le'olam haba*,
and in the world to come, God will so that's the בהקיץ
*behakitz*. So you'll be wide awake in the world to come, maybe
sometimes you're learning at 4 AM and you're only halfway or whatever,
the world to come you will be wide awake and fully able
to learn all the time and be in God's presence. Okay, fine.
אמר רבי יוחנן מאי דכתיב *amar Rabbi Yochanan mai dechtiv*, מלוה ה'
חונן דל *malveh Hashem chonen dal*, so the creditor to God, this
is the way the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is reading it, the one
who lends money to God is the one who does kindness to
the poor. ושלמו ישלם לו *vshalmo yeshalem lo*, מקרא כתוב *mikra katuv*,
this is how it's reading. אי אפשר לאומרו *i efshar le'omro*, were
it not for the pasuk was written you could not say such
a thing. כביכול עבד לוה לאיש מלוה *keviyachol eved loveh le'ish malveh*,
it's as if saying that God is your servant because if you
are like a creditor to God then you know you have a
power over God as if as if right so but the point
so it's that is the power of צדקה *tzedakah*. But by the
way, עבד לוה לאיש מלוה *eved loveh le'ish malveh* isn't God is
the לוה *loveh*, you're the מלוה *malveh*. כביכול *keviyachol*, what? I thought
we're the עבד *eved*... No, no, no. עבד לוה לאיש מלוה *eved
loveh le'ish malveh* means the borrower is a slave. slave to the
creditor, to the lender. I mean, it's not the פשט pshat of
the פסוק. It's not the פשט of the פסוק. So once it's
saying you are God's creditor, imagine if we would apply the normal
relationship of creditor to borrower and so you know, then what does
that mean about your relationship to God? I know, it's very theological,
it's just I understand, I understand, but we're reading it as the
opposite and have it mean what it means. Okay, I'm not going
to debate this. That is what the גמרא Gemara. means, okay? Go
take a look at רש״י. Rashi. חונה דלים מלוה הקדוש ברוך הוא
Choneh dalim malveh l'Hakadosh Baruch Hu וכתיב ועבד לוה לאיש מלוה. ve'chsiv
ve'eved loveh l'ish malveh. Okay, anyway, so that's the point. Now, part
of the point I think is, if you and again, rather than
just sort of saying, oh wow, look at this power, it's that
it goes back to the question of, right, should I really be
giving money? I mean, I only have so much money, how much
should I be giving to צדקה? You know, it's sort of like
what the גמרא Gemara says by שבת, Shabbos? right? What does the
גמרא Gemara say by שבת? Shabbos, לו עלי ואני אשלם. Lavu alay
va'ani ashalem. Borrow money for me, spend money on שבת, on יום
טוב, Yom Tov, and I will pay you back. Right. So here
it's saying if you give money to the poor person, it's like
you know you've lent money to God. God is now in your
debt and God is going to have to repay that debt to
you. God pays you back. Okay, so that I think is the
image that we're really trying to get at, not just this sort
of, you know, you're God's creditor. Okay. אמר רבי חייא בר אבא
רבי יוחנן רמי. Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba Rabbi Yochanan rami. Rabbi
Yochanan shows a conflict between פסוקים. psukim. כתיב לא יועיל הון ביום
עברה וצדקה תציל ממות. Ksiv lo yo'il hon b'yom evrah utzedakah tatzil
mimaves. The wealth will not help at the on the day of
anger and צדקה will save from death. וכתיב לא יועילו אוצרות רשע.
uch'shiv lo yo'ilu otzros resha. The wealth, the you know the storehouses
of a רשע maybe, the storehouses of the wicked person will not
help him, it doesn't do you any good, you can't take your
money with you. Okay. וצדקה תציל ממות. So what should you do
with the money? Don't keep it in your bank account, give צדקה,
צדקה will save from death. So it's not a contradiction, but it's
basically a repetition. So it says, שתי צדקות הללו למה? Shtei tzedakos
hallalu lamah? Why do you need to tell me twice צדקה saves
from death? אחת שמצילתו ממיתה משונה. Achas she'matzilaso mimisah meshunah. One will
save you from a, you know, from a painful death in this
world, a painful or disfiguring death in this world, you'll die a
peaceful death. And obviously it doesn't really save you from death, everybody
dies. ואחת שמצילתו מדינה של גיהנום. Ve'achas she'matzilaso midinah shel Gehennom. The
other will save you from the fate worse than death, from the
punishment in גיהנום. Gehennom. ואיזו היא שמצילתו מדינה של גיהנום? Ve'eizo hi
she'matzilaso midinah shel Gehennom? Which is the one that will save you
from גיהנום? Gehennom? ההוא דכתיב ביה עברה. Hahu d'ksiv bei evrah. The
one that says it will save you from anger. דכתיב יום עברה
היום ההוא. d'ksiv yom evrah hayom hahu. That day of judgment, day
of anger. ואיזו היא שמצילתו ממיתה משונה? Ve'eizo hi she'matzilaso mimisah meshunah?
Which one is going to save you from a perverse death in
this world? נותנה ואינו יודע למי נותנה. Nosenah ve'eino yodea l'mi nosenah.
It is if you give צדקה in the really ideal way. You
give it and you don't know who it's going to. נוטלה ואינו
יודע ממי נוטלה. Notlah ve'eino yodea mimi notlah. And when the person
takes it, he doesn't know who gave it to him, right? The
Rambam has his eight stages of lending money or whatever. He didn't
make it up, right? It's obviously based on the גמרא. Gemara The
גמרא Gemara doesn't sort of organize it that way, but the best
צדקה is you don't know who is receiving it and the person
who gets it doesn't know who's giving it. Okay, and now the
גמרא Gemara says like this. נותנה ואינו יודע למי נותנה. Nosenah ve'eino
yodea l'mi nosenah. You give it and you don't know you don't
know who you're giving it to. לאפוקי. le'apukei Here's that לאפוקי again.
In contrast to מדמר עוקבא. mi'demar Ukva. What Mar Ukva used to
do. Not like Mar Ukva would disagree and say and he would
presumably agree that this is the best, you know, to be able
to give you know do it in both ways, but the way
he would normally give would be the following way. Okay, מדמר עוקבא.
mi'demar Ukva. נוטלה ואינו יודע ממי נוטלה. Notlah ve'eino yodea mimi notlah.
And the עני ani? not knowing who he is taking from. לאפוקי
מרבי אבא. le'apukei m'Rabbi Abba. To in contrast to the way Rabbi
Abba would classically give. אלא היכי ליעביד? Ella heichi liyavid? So how'd
you do this to achieve anonymity on both sides? ליתיב לארנקי של
צדקה. Leisiv l'arneki shel tzedakah. You give it to a middleman, you
give it to the person who's running a charity fund, and that
person, you know, keeps your identity private, you know, you know, private
and keeps the identity of the one who receives it private and
nobody knows who the giver is and the receiver is. מיתיבי. Meisivei.
מה יעשה אדם ויהיו לו בנים זכרים? Mah ya'aseh adam veyihyu lo
banim zacharim? What should a person do to have male children? Because
obviously in the time of the גמרא Gemara, that was seen as,
you know, in a patriarchal society, people more highly want to have
male children. Or a cultural society, I mean just lots of... Right,
like in China or whatever, all these cases, right, you know, people,
you know, it's... Right, so if you want to, what should you
do to merit this? רבי אליעזר אומר יפזר מעותיו לעניים. Rabbi Eliezer
omer yefazer me'osav le'aniyim. Scatter your money to the poor. Obviously the
word יפזר yefazer is funny, we haven't yet I think seen that
word yet, but it means like don't be so careful, right? Just
give with, you know, prolifically, you know, without, you know, and like
don't, you know, just scatter your money, give to anybody who asks.
Okay, Rabbi Yehoshua says, and give a lot. רבי יהושע אומר ישמח
אשתו בדבר מצוה. Rabbi Yehoshua omer yisammach ishto b'dvar mitzvah. He should
rejoice his wife in the matter of מצוה, which means in marital
sex, so he should take care of his wife's needs and be
responsive to his wife. Very different types of responses, but you know,
what what do they have to do, I mean this at least
his thing is connected to the wanting to have certain kids. You
want to have male children, so it's dealing with when the children
are conceived. How this relates to giving your money to the poor,
how the first thing connects to male children, I don't. רבי אליעזר
בן יעקב אומר, Rebbi Eliezer ben Yaakov Omer, now this is still
part of this ברייתא, braita, because so far it's not relevant to
us. רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer directly says, לא יתן אדם פרוטה לעני
של צדקה אלא אם כן ממונה עליו כרבי חנניה בן תרדיון. Lo
yitten adam peruta le'ani shel tzedakah ella im ken memunah alav keRebbi
Chananya ben Teradyon. Since the first opinion רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer mentioned
that you're supposed to scatter your money to the poor, so within
this ברייתא, there's רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer, excuse me, יעקב is saying,
be careful when you give your money to the poor. You know,
don't give it to a middleman, maybe it's reinforcing the יפזר yefazer
more, but give it directly to the poor. You should not give
it to some middleman, to some צדקה collector, unless they are somebody
who is as trustworthy as רבי חנניה בן תרדיון. Rebbi Chananya ben
Teradyon. So, how can you say the best way to give is
anonymity on both sides and to give it to a צדקה collector,
if they're only supposed to give it to those that are really
trustworthy? So the answer is obvious, כי קאמינא דממנו עליה כרבי חנניה
בן תרדיון. Ki kamina demamnu aleih keRebbi Chananya ben Teradyon. Fine, what
I'm talking about is when you have a trustworthy צדקה. And by
the way, there's a really important point. People that are really thoughtful
about their giving want to look into the funds that are collecting.
How much overhead is there, you know, try to have minimal overhead,
how good are they about really, you know, using the money wisely
and how trustworthy are they to use, you know, to do the
right stuff with your money. So it's a very good to do
it this way, but you have to be responsible. What about the
גמרא a couple of דפים daphim ago that says not to look
into the trustworthiness or that of the individual עני? Right, no, no,
no, it was the who on clothes, on clothes? No, is it
that... right, that's a good point, that's sort of once... that's not
to, I think that that is like, you should, I think that
was a little bit more like there's like a before and an
after. Like before I give my money I should sort of make
a smart decision, once, but when they're in their role I should
not be suspecting them. The גמרא before was like when they're doing
their job they should be assumed to be above suspicion and they
have to act that way, etc., etc. But you're right, I mean,
this is an important corrective or counterbalance to that. Just because we're
saying they should be above suspicion when they're doing their job doesn't
mean that you should be like not careful when you're making, you
know, when you're thinking about whether to give it to them. Okay.
Let's try to get a little bit further. אמר רבי אבהו אמר
משה לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא. Amar Rebbi Abbahu amar Moshe lifnei haKadosh
Baruch Hu. משה Moshe said to God, ריבונו של עולם, Ribbono shel
Olam, Master of the Universe, במה תרום קרן ישראל? Bameh tarum keren
Yisrael? How will the horn of Israel be raised up? What will
raise their status in the world? אמר לו בכי תשא. Amar lo
beKi Tisa. בכי תשא beKi Tisa at the head of the children
of ישראל. Yisrael. If you want to lift up their heads, how
do you do it? So what's כי תשא Ki Tisa about? Giving
money to the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. We're translating בית המקדש Beit
Hamikdash into צדקה. ויאמר רבי אבהו שאלו שלמה בן דוד ואיה שלמה,
Vayomer Rebbi Abbahu sha'alu Shlomo ben David ve'ayei Shlomo, דוד's David king,
דוד's David son, דוד's David son, עד היכן כוחה של צדקה? Ad
heichan kocha shel tzedakah? How powerful is צדקה? אמר להם צאו וראו
מה פירש דוד אבא. Amar lahem tze'u ur'u mah peireish David abba.
Go and look what my father wrote. פזר נתן לאביונים, Pizer natan
la'evyonim, again this word פזר, pizer, to scatter, like, you know, he
gave of his money to the poor, scattered his money to the
poor. צדקתו עומדת לעד, Tzidkato omedet la'ad, it'll stand forever, right? I
mean קרנו תרום בכבוד, Karno tarum bechavod, his horn again that's תרום
tarum from before, his horn will be lifted up in honor, so
he'll have this everlasting honor. רבי אבא מיהא אמר מהכא. Rebbi Abba
meiha amar mehacha. הוא מרומים ישכון, Hu meromim yishkon, he will dwell
on high. מצדות סלעים משגבו, Metzadot sela'im misgavo, his dwelling place will
be in the, you know, in the protective places of the rocks.
לחמו נתן מימיו נאמנים, Lachmo nutan meimav ne'emanim, his bread he has
given, his waters are faithful. מה טעם מרומים ישכון מצדות סלעים משגבו?
Mah ta'am meromim yishkon metzadot sela'im misgavo? Why does he dwell on
high? משום דלחמו נתן ומימיו נאמנים Mishum delachmo nutan umeimav ne'emanim because
he provided for the poor. Okay. ואמר רבי אבהו שאלו שלמה, Ve'amar
Rebbi Abbahu sha'alu Shlomo, they asked שלמה, Shlomo, איזהו בן עולם הבא?
Eizehu ben Olam Haba? Who's going to get the world to come?
אמר להם כל שכנגד זקניו כבוד. Amar lahem kol shekeneged zekenav kavod.
Anybody that in his old age he is being honored. So that's,
if you look at רש"י Rashi it says עושים שחולקים להם כבוד
בעולם הזה מחמת חכמתם, Osim shecholkim lahem kavod ba'olam hazeh machmat chochmatam,
people that are respected, not מחמת חכמת תורתם, machmat chochmat toratam, people
who are respected for their sort of like the wisdom of their
experience by people that are, you know... That's what רש"י Rashi says?
Where it says, where is it? כנגד זקניו כבוד, Keneged zekenav kavod,
it's six lines down in the wide lines. So that's right, that's
powerful, right? Not people that are respected, but people who are respected
because of the wisdom, the wisdom that they've achieved, you know, over,
you know, in their years. Those are the people that you know
will get עולם הבא. Olam Haba. So there's a little bit diverting
from the צדקה theme, but we're asking שלמה Shlomo how certain things
happen, maybe because he was חכם מכל אדם, chacham mikol adam, we
want to know certain, you know, they're saying this was asked of
שלמה. Shlomo. כל שכנגד זקניו כבוד. Kol shekeneged zekenav kavod. So כי
הא ד, Ki ha de, now, like the story דיוסף בריה דרבי
יהושע חלש, DeYosef bereih deRebbi Yehoshua chalash, he got sick, אינגיד, Ingid,
he like fainted, you know, he almost like, he looked like he
had died, he recovered, he, you know, he revived. אמר ליה אבוה
מאי חזית. Amar leih avuh mai chazit. So like, what did you
see, you know, when people having a near-death experience, like what did
you see when you sort of fainted, we thought you were dead,
and then you came back? What'd you see? I think, what? Yeah,
אמר ליה, amar leh, this is such a, you know, famous גמרא,
עולם הפוך ראיתי. Olam hafuch ra'iti. A world I saw, the world
to come is upside down from this world. עליונים למטה ותחתונים למעלה.
Elyonim lemata vetachtonim lemala. The people are who here are at the
top, that are given the most honor, the people with the most
wealth or whatever, they're at the bottom there, you know, doesn't mean
that there's anything wrong with having money, but, you know, they're often,
you know, works that, you know, whatever, that things are not in
this world according to merit. Okay, ותחתונים למטה ve-tachtonim lemata and the
people over here at the bottom over there because they're poor, and
maybe this is going back to the whole Turnus Rufus discussion, and
they're seen as, you know, at the bottom of the sort of
social scale, there they're at the top. אמר ליה, amar leh, עולם
ברור ראית, Olam barur ra'ita, actually that world, that was the true
world. ואנן היכי חזינא, ve-anan heichi chazina, now how about the Rabbis?
What's, where do they stand in the world to come? אמר ליה,
amar leh, כי היכי דחשבינן הכא חשבינן התם. Ki heichi dechashvinan hacha
chashvinan hatam. The same respect we have here, we have there. Notice
he didn't say, oh, we're at the top. Right, this gets back
to the point of that, you know, the respect that you garner
in this world for the things that deserve respect, not for your
money and power. That's irrespective, you know, then it's going to be
the opposite in the world to come or whatever, not related. But
the things that you garner respect for in this world that deserve
respect, your תורה Torah and your חכמה, that is a reflection of
the level that you'll have in the world to come. ושמעתי שהיו
אומרים, veshamati shehayu omrim, and I heard that they used to say,
אשרי מי שבא לכאן ותלמודו בידו. ashrei mi sheba lechan vetalmudo beyado.
Praised is the person who comes here and his learning is in
his hand. So there's a beautiful מהרש"א, Maharsha, Rabbi Dov, listen up
because this is a pedagogical point. He says what does it mean
learning is in his hand? So it says it means the stuff
that he remembers and he really owns, why? Because he wrote it
down. It's בידו. beyado. Okay, which is like I'm always telling my
students, you know, people nowadays are sitting in a class and their
mind wanders and what do they do, they surf the web. In
my days, what did you do when your mind wandered? You'd doodle.
And when you doodle, like they really show that it really actually
helps you think, you know? So it's תלמודו בידו. talmudo beyado. Okay.
ושמעתי שהיו אומרים, veshamati shehayu omrim, and I heard that they used
to say, הרוגי מלכות אין כל בריה יכולה לעמוד במחיצתם. harugei malchus
ein kol berya yechola la'amod bimchitzatam. Those that have been killed, you
know, martyred themselves because of קידוש השם Kiddush Hashem by the government,
or by the Roman government, nobody can reach their level. מאן נינהו?
Man ninhu? Now who are we talking about? רבי עקיבא וחבריו? Rabbi
Akiva vechaverav? The great Rabbis who died, you know, in the Roman
persecutions. משום הרוגי מלכות הוו בהא דרגא? Mishum harugei malchus havu behai
darga? Are they in a high level in the world to come
just because they are martyrs? פשיטא דבלאו הכי נמי. Pshita delav hachi
nami. They would be in the highest level in the world to
come even without having been martyred. אלא הרוגי לוד, Ela harugei Lod,
those that were martyred in the story of לוד, Lod, and רש"י
Rashi tells the whole sort of story about that, about two brothers,
the Roman government was going to wipe out a whole city because
of, it was like a blood libel, a suspect of who killed
this, this person, and these two brothers admitted that they had done
it. They hadn't done it, but they did it in order to
save the whole city. Okay, I guess we will have to end
here. But we're getting much closer to being caught up. Rabbi Dov.